<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The only legal answer which constables and church-wardens may give to articles inquiring into any of His majesties ecclesiastical or civil courts, or to any justices upon the Statutes 1 Eliz. 2 and 3 Jac. 4 concerning the absence of persons from their parish-church in a letter to a private friend, inquiring on the behalf of his friend, the sense and import of those statutes in this case, and whether officers can be required by a particular oath, to give in answers to such articles, and how often.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53378</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12988506</idno>
  <idno type="VID">96259</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240919672</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing O348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6699</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12988506</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53378)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 724:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The only legal answer which constables and church-wardens may give to articles inquiring into any of His majesties ecclesiastical or civil courts, or to any justices upon the Statutes 1 Eliz. 2 and 3 Jac. 4 concerning the absence of persons from their parish-church in a letter to a private friend, inquiring on the behalf of his friend, the sense and import of those statutes in this case, and whether officers can be required by a particular oath, to give in answers to such articles, and how often.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church attendance --  Law and legislation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96259:1"/>
            <p>THE Only Legal Answer WHICH CONSTABLES AND CHURCH-WARDENS MAY GIVE TO ARTICLES Inquiring into any of His MAJESTIES Ecclesiastical or Civil COURTS; OR TO ANY JUSTICES upon the Statutes 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. and 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 4. Concerning the absence of persons from their PARISH-CHURCH. IN A LETTER to a private Friend, Inquiring on the behalf of his Friend, the sense and import of those Statutes in this case; and whether Officers can be required by a particular Oath, to give in Answers to such Articles, and how often.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96259:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96259:2"/>
            <head>The only Legal Answer which Constables and Church-Wardens may give to Articles inquiring in any of his Majesties Ecclesiastical or Civil Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have received yours, with your request in it on the behalf of your Friend, who you say is made <hi>Constable,</hi> and required to present offenders upon Fourteen Articles, first sent to the Constables, but to do it upon <hi>Oath,</hi> yea, and to do it not only before each ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Quarter Sessions and Assizes,</hi> which is Six times each year; but every <hi>month,</hi> upon some <hi>Justices meeting,</hi> so often near you, or within the <hi>Division.</hi> One of which Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, you say is, <hi>Whether he knows of any that for the three precedent Sundays came not to their Parish Church to hear Divine Service;</hi> and that if their presentment do not please them, <hi>they will not take them;</hi> and if any be presented, they ordinarily issue out their Warrants by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stress of goods, to levy 12 <hi>d.</hi> for every days absence; which if they cannot get, they presently send the persons to Gaol. You say the <hi>Constables</hi> are required to give in their presentments upon a particular Oath then given (not only by vertue of their general Oath given them at their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Office). You desire my advice in the case. <hi>Sir,</hi> you know I am for going to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service,</hi> I hope you are so too; so as you are only concerned for your Friend.</p>
            <p>I very much suspect that the <hi>Justices,</hi> who are so active, are little skilled in the Law; I will assure you we have no such doings on this side of the <hi>Thames:</hi> Possibly it is our advantage to be so near the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> and <hi>Chancery,</hi> and so near <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> where now it is so easie to get a Writ of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> and persons can go up in a Boat for Three or four Shillings, whereas you are so much within Land, that men are scared at three or four Pound charge to bring up themselves to the <hi>Kings Bench:</hi> It will be therefore a little charitable to relieve you; but when I have said all I can, <hi>Justices</hi> may send men to <hi>Gaol</hi> if they will, right or wrong, if they have not courage enough to try the legality of such imprisonment before the wiser <hi>Judges of the Land,</hi> which the Law gives any one leave to do; but we say in our Law, <hi>Lex non est posita dormientibus sed vigilantibus.</hi> But to your business; I am so far from being able to tell you, that <hi>Justices</hi> of Peace may require you upon a <hi>new Oath</hi> to present upon <hi>Articles,</hi> that I cannot tell upon what <hi>Law</hi> those <hi>Articles</hi> are founded, or any presenting upon <hi>Articles</hi> required: I know no <hi>Statute-Law</hi> for it. Our <hi>Common Law</hi> is the ancient <hi>Custom</hi> and <hi>usage of the Nation;</hi> now I cannot find that there is any usage of such thing, that can prescribe to Fifty years. About Eight or Nine years before the Civil Wars, I remember some such thing, but not before that time (which makes no custom); then it was discontinued Twenty years: This is all the <hi>Antiquity</hi> I can find for <hi>Articles.</hi> But for Answers to <hi>Articles</hi> to be given in to <hi>Justices</hi> upon an <hi>Oath</hi> given them at the time of their giving in such Answers, it is more than I know if there be any <hi>Statute</hi> or <hi>Common Law</hi> for it; if I mistake not, it is a perfect <hi>Innovation;</hi> and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks discreet <hi>Justices</hi> should be wary how they give <hi>Oathes</hi> in cases not <hi>warranted by Law,</hi> it being a business of more than ordinary danger, which I should hardly venture upon, or commit any person that should refuse so to charge himself.</p>
            <p>We have <hi>Statute-oaths</hi> enough, and need not to multiply them. I fear that the violation of our legal Oaths lyes as no mean guilt upon us; and upon that account, if there were no <hi>civil liberty</hi> concerned in it, I should be well assured that a person had authority <hi>to give me an oath in the ease</hi> before I should take it.</p>
            <p>I do very well know that we have many Statutes that are inquirable of by Justices, some only at the <hi>Assizes</hi> or <hi>Sessions,</hi> some out of Sessions; but in order to the trial of offenders there, or at the <hi>Assizes;</hi> Somewhere they may take Examinations upon Oath, as in cases of <hi>Treason</hi> or <hi>Feleny;</hi> but as to this business of not coming to hear Divine Service, I do not know that any Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture directs Justices of Peace out of Sessions to examine any upon Oath, much less to command Ossicers under an Oath to answer to any <hi>Articles of that nature;</hi> nor that the Law requires Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers upon Oath to present any person, either at Assizes, or Sessions, for <hi>not coming to their Parish-Church to hear Divine Service,</hi> more than to present any whom within twenty days before they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96259:3"/>have heard prophanely swear and curse contrary to the <hi>Stat.</hi> 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 20. or such as <hi>profane the Sabbath day,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Stat.</hi> 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. or the late <hi>Act</hi> of the same nature; or such as keep <hi>Ale houses</hi> without license, contrary to the <hi>Stat.</hi> 3 <hi>Car.</hi> 3. Or such as are <hi>drunk</hi> contrary to the <hi>Stat</hi> 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 5.21 <hi>Jac.</hi> 7. Or <hi>staying longer in an Ale house</hi> than the Statute alloweth, 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 5. Offences against any Statute-Laws as to Morality, are inquirable into by Justices of the Peace in their Sessions, and Officers may there present persons guilty of any violation of them; but that they are more obliged by the Law to present <hi>offences</hi> of this nature, than other, is more than I know; and therefore the Articles (if it shall please Justices to give out any to inform Officers) should comprehend all such <hi>crimes,</hi> and not some only, for that is ready to beget an error in Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, That they are bound to present upon no other Statutes, or that the Court can inquire of no other; which is a great error. There is as much law to present and indite any for <hi>profane swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cursing,</hi> for <hi>violating the Sabbath,</hi> for <hi>being drunk,</hi> or <hi>sitting at an Alehouse tipling,</hi> as for <hi>not coming to Church;</hi> and I do not know that any Officer can be under an obligation to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent one more than another.</p>
            <p>Nay, perhaps if we look into the Laws in this case, we shall find them more concerned; there are three Statutes about coming to Church, that 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> the two latter are but Commentaries on the former, or <hi>appendices</hi> to it. The Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> mentions no <hi>Constables;</hi> nay in the <hi>levy</hi> of the fine, makes it the work of <hi>Churchwardens,</hi> not <hi>Constables.</hi> But divers of the other Statutes expresly charge the <hi>Constables</hi> with levying the penalties. So that under savour, I understand not by what law any Justices command Constables to levy any fines upon that Statute, when the Statute expresly saith it shall be <hi>levied by the Churchwardens of the Parish.</hi> This is enough, <hi>Sir,</hi> as to requiring Constables to present upon Oath, that is a new Oath repeated so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they do present; nay to <hi>present at all, offenders</hi> upon that Statute more than upon all other Statutes of which those Courts may take cognizance.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Sir,</hi> I very much doubt, whether Justices can by enquiry proceed upon the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> out of Sessions; the Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> plainly limiteth the Enquiry to Justices of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirminer,</hi> and Justices of Assize. So that by that Statute, <hi>Justices of the Peace</hi> only cannot med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the execution of it; but after this cometh the Stat. 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and giveth Justices of the Peace a power to enquire upon this Statute, but saith nothing of <hi>determining.</hi> After this comes the Stat. 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 4. that provides,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if any subject of this Realm at any time within one month after the end of this present Session of Parliament, shall not resort to repair to some Church or Chappel, or some other usual place appointed for Common-Prayer, and there hear Divine Service according to the Statute made in that behalf in the first year of the reign of the late Queen</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>that then it shall and may be lawful for any one Justice of Peace of that Limit, Division, or Liberty, wherein the said party shall dwell, upon proof unto him made by confession of the party, or oath of witness, to call the said party before him; and if he or she, shall not make a sufficient excuse, and make due proof thereof, to the satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the said Justice of Peace; that it shall be lawful for the said Justice of Peace to give Warrant to the Churchwarden of such Parish wherein such party shall dwell, under his hand and seal, to levy Twelve-pence by distress, and sale of the goods of every such offender, rendring to the offender the overplus of the money raised of the said goods so to be sold. And that in default of such distress, it shall and may be lawful for such Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of the Peace to commit any such offender to some Prison within the said Shire, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, limit, or liberty, where such offender shall inhabit, until payment be made of such sum or sums so to be forfeited, which forfeiture shall be employed to and for the use of the poor of that Parish wherein the offender shall be resident, or abiding at the time of such offence committed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided that no man shall be impeached upon this clause except he be called in question for his default within one month after the said default made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then afterward it saith, <hi>That all offences against that Act, other than</hi> Treason, <hi>shall be enquired, heard and determined before the Justices of Peace in their</hi> General Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Sessions <hi>to be holden in the Shire, division, limit, or liberty, wherein such offence shall happen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96259:3"/>
            <p>The Statute 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> limited the enquiry and determination of such offences to Justices of <hi>Assize,</hi> and to Justices of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Determiner,</hi> and to the next <hi>Assizes</hi> or <hi>Quarter-Sessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> the Statute 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> gave <hi>Justices of the Peace</hi> a power to <hi>enquire,</hi> but not to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. The Stat. 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> 4. gives any one <hi>Justice of the Peace,</hi> a power to determine <hi>upon proof</hi> made of this offence, but limits an <hi>enquiry, hearing</hi> and <hi>determining</hi> to the <hi>general Quarter-Sessions.</hi> I conceive by that Statute one Justice of Peace, if any will voluntarily complain and make proof of this offence out of Sessions, may hear it and determine; but he cannot enquire by commanding officers to present and make proof, but in the <hi>General Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Sessions,</hi> and all within a months time. But I pray observe that Statute.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The offence must be <hi>not resorting to some Parish Church or Chappel, or some other place appointed to hear Common Prayer.</hi> No Officer by vertue of that Statute can present any for not coming to his or their Parish-Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Proof must be made of the offences:</hi> I do not think the presentment of any Officer <hi>ex Officio</hi> is a proof by the Law of <hi>England,</hi> which is evident in all presentments by <hi>Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> which are no proofs; yet they reasonably ought to be judged so before <hi>petty Constables</hi> presentments.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Prosecution which by 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is limited to the next Assizes or Sessions, and by the 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> enlarged to a year and a day, is here restrained to a month after the offence is committed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By this Statute, <hi>the Warrant for distress must be to the Churchwardens, not to the Constables.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Before the conviction the party must have a liberty to make and prove his excuse, if he hath any.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I enlarge the more upon this Statute, because I perceive by your story, that this is that which your Justices proceed upon; for you say they meet <hi>monthly,</hi> and imprison presently for want of <hi>distress,</hi> which no other Statute gives them liberty to do. I say, according to this <hi>Act,</hi> if Officers will upon articles present, they must say, that the party was not at <hi>some Church and Chappel;</hi> it is not enough for them to say he was not at his <hi>Parish-Church,</hi> that Statute saith no such thing. Nor doth it give any Justice a power to <hi>enquire out of Sessions,</hi> only to <hi>hear and act upon proof voluntarily brought to him.</hi> So that I can see no Statute they can proceed upon, but that 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> that indeed inflicts the same 12 <hi>d.</hi> punishment upon those who <hi>having no reasonable let or excuse, come not to their Parish-Church, or in let thereof, to some other.</hi> But that 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> saith nothing of this or that <hi>Parish-Church;</hi> and by the Stat. 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> they cannot <hi>imprison</hi> for want of <hi>distress presently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed I cannot understand by what pretence of Law any thus proceeds: for our Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth <hi>certainty,</hi> and will not allow a man for the same offence to be prosecuted upon <hi>two Statutes,</hi> though relating to the same offence. The <hi>Justices</hi> indeed may chuse what <hi>Statute</hi> they will proceed upon, but they can proceed but upon one at the same time. The Justices you speak of, proceed upon the <hi>crime</hi> mentioned only in the Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> but then they pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish by the Stat. 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> and enquire into the offence by the Warrant of no Statute (out of Sessions) that I can find. I can only say, if this be Law, I do not understand; only <hi>blots</hi> are no <hi>blots till they be hit;</hi> but I should be loth either to <hi>enquire</hi> upon any offence, or to <hi>commit any</hi> after this rate, for fear of an <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> and an <hi>action of false imprisonment,</hi> and something worse than that; the Law of <hi>England</hi> hath set inferiour Magistrates their bounds, for giving <hi>Oaths</hi> in cases, and for sending men to Prisons.</p>
            <p>But if your friend be in no capacity, or hath not stomack enough to try those issues, I do not yet understand why, if he will put himself to such frequent troubles, but he may present legally, and never run any danger of perjury. To this purpose let us consider the Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which is plainly the Text to which both the Stat. of 23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> do both refer; the words of that Statute are these.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that from and after the said Feast of the Nativity of St.</hi> John Baptist <hi>next coming, all and every person or persons, inhabiting within this Realm, or any other the Queens Majesties Dominions, shall diligently and faithfully, having no lawful and reasonable excuse to be absent, endeavour themselves to resort to their Parish-Church, or Chappel accustomed, or upon reasonable let thereof, to some usual place, where Common-Prayer and such Service of God shall be used in such time of let upon every Sunday, and other days ordained to be kept as Holidays, and then and there to abide orderly, and soberly, during the time of the Common-Prayer,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96259:4"/>Preaching, or other service of God there to be used and ministred, upon pain of the censures of the Church, and also upon pain that every person so offending shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit for every such offence Twelve pence to be levied by the Churchwardens of the Parish where such offence shall be done, to the use of the poor of the same Parish, of the goods, lands, and tenements of such offenders, by way of distress.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The question is, what the <hi>crime</hi> was which the wisdom of Parliament at this time thought fit to provide against by this Act? and what it could be other than mens <hi>profane spending of that time which the Church had set apart to the service of God,</hi> I cannot understand. For <hi>Parliaments</hi> use to proceed not against crimes not in being, but against all manners that do appear. For any pretendedly religious spending of that time other than at Church, either by <hi>Papists</hi> or <hi>Protestants,</hi> it was a crime not then committed by any, and therefore not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided against by the Stat. 1 <hi>Eliz. Papists</hi> generally went to hear <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> ten years, till the Popes <hi>Bulls</hi> came out; and the <hi>Protestants</hi> that were like to keep <hi>Conventicles,</hi> were not yet come over from beyond Sea, whither they were driven by Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Persecution; nor do we find in our Statutes a word about <hi>Conventicles</hi> till the Stat. 35 <hi>Eliz</hi> which was at least 34. years after this. But at this time without doubt there were a company of <hi>Atheisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal persons</hi> in the Nation who would rather spend these days at <hi>Alchouses and Taverns,</hi> or <hi>idly walking up and down, or at some sports,</hi> or <hi>in their beds,</hi> than at the Worship of God; against whom this <hi>Act</hi> seems, if not chiefly, to be made; and only this clause in the Act in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> then knew, that a very great part of the Subjects could not yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this <hi>Precept,</hi> being <hi>sick,</hi> or <hi>from home,</hi> or <hi>attending the necessary concerns of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> and there being no <hi>Divine Service</hi> at many Churches at that time, and therefore could not be conceived to make all absent from their <hi>Parish-Church</hi> criminal; nor do they, but only those that are <hi>absent without any reasonable let or excuse.</hi> This then is the crime, <hi>to be absent from the Parish Church without reasonable let or excuse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither can the wisdom of <hi>Parliament</hi> be presumed to have directed, that <hi>Officers</hi> should present <hi>all that were absent without reasonable let or excuse;</hi> for how should Officers know this? they must know the state of every body in their Parish, whether they were in health or sickness; the circumstances of every person; whether he were at home that day, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; the order of every <hi>family;</hi> what servants were necessary to be at home to look after young children; what persons were nurses to sick persons, what Physicians or Apothecaries were attending sick persons; which is both impossible and unreasonable to suppose. There can be no possible obligation upon any to present, farther than according to their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, for they are upon their Oaths. There seems therefore no Article to be well drawn upon this Statute, but this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you know of any person in your Parish, who having no reasonable let or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, doth not endeavour to resort to his Parish-Church or Chappel accustomed, or upon some reasonable let thereof, to some other place where Common-Prayer or such service of God is used in such time of let, upon every Sunday, and other days or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be kept as Holidays, and there abide orderly and soberly during the time of Common-Prayer, Preaching, or other Service of God there to be used and ministred?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In case the Officer doth know of any who hath no reasonable let or impediment, that is who is neither <hi>sick,</hi> or <hi>abroad,</hi> nor <hi>detained at home by necessary occasions,</hi> but spends his, or her time, those days, at <hi>Alchouses</hi> and <hi>Taverns,</hi> or in <hi>idle recreations,</hi> or <hi>in his bed,</hi> or at any <hi>unlawful meetings,</hi> he is bound to present them; otherwise he seems not bound by this Statute, but may rather answer thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We do not know of any person in our Parish who having no reasonable let or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse doth not endeavour to resort to his Parish-Church or Chappel accustomed, or upon reasonable let thereof to some other place where Common-Prayer or such Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God is used in such time of let upon every Sunday, and other days ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be kept as Holidays.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96259:4"/>
            <p>And if it be put in the Article (as it should) according to the Statute, <hi>and there abide during the time of Common-Prayer, Preaching, or other Service of God there to be used and ministred, orderly and soberly:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he knows any that being at Church spend their time in <hi>sleeping</hi> or <hi>talking,</hi> or the like, he is obliged to present them; if not, he may answer in the words of the Statute: <hi>Nor of any who do not there abide orderly and soberly during the time of Common Prayer, Preaching, or other Service of God there used and ministred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Article</hi> be formed upon the Stat. 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> let the answer be still in the words of the Statute: <hi>We do not know of any who within a month last past have not resorted to some Church or Chappel, or some usual place appointed for Common-Prayer, and there hear Divine Service, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute made in that behalf in the first year of Queen</hi> Elizabeth.</p>
            <p>These are the very words of the <hi>Statute,</hi> according to which all <hi>Articles,</hi> and <hi>Answers,</hi> or <hi>Presentments</hi> in any of his <hi>Majesties</hi> Courts <hi>Ecclestiastical</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> are requisite to be drawn; no inferiour <hi>Officer</hi> being to answer in any other terms than what shall sully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that sense; for <hi>inferiour Officers</hi> are not to <hi>present</hi> according to the <hi>wills</hi> of any, but only according to the <hi>letter of the Law,</hi> which is the common Rule of both: And you may assure your Friend, that any <hi>Judges</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will so determine. Which if they will, if any Country <hi>Justice</hi> will venture once to <hi>commit</hi> any to Prison because he will answer no otherwise; if he brings his Writ of <hi>Hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as Corpus,</hi> the Justice will understand how to take heed of his duty the next time.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell your Friend how to avoid a Prison, if an adventurous Justice will send him; it is enough for me to tell him how he may come out when he is there, and have his charges paid for the time he stays there.</p>
            <p>Let not your Friend be frighted therefore with such stories; It would be pretty news to us in <hi>Westminster Hall,</hi> to hear of any <hi>Justice</hi> that should refuse an answer to <hi>Articles</hi> founded upon a <hi>Statute,</hi> given them in the words of the <hi>Statute:</hi> We should adventure to tell them, they assumed a <hi>Legislative power</hi> to themselves, and that their business is to <hi>execute Laws,</hi> not to <hi>make them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you say, they tell him that <hi>he must present all those that are not at Church; the Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces must judge of his excuse whether it be reasonable or no.</hi> This it is for men not to consult the <hi>Statute,</hi> which saith no such thing. This indeed would bring in a fine revenue to the <hi>Clerks of the Sessions,</hi> or those belonging to the <hi>Justices;</hi> but <hi>absence from Church,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding, <hi>having no reasonable excuse, is by the Statute no crime:</hi> as you may see by the words of the Statute before recited. It is true, if any be voluntarily complained of by some <hi>Informer, the Justices</hi> by the <hi>Statute</hi> 3 <hi>Jac.</hi> must send for the party, and hear what excuse he hath, and how he can prove it; and till that be done, the person is in Law no offender. But when Officers present upon Oath, they present none but <hi>offenders,</hi> and those who they know are offenders; and they can know none to be such, unless they know <hi>that he is absent,</hi> having <hi>no reasonable let or excuse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Sir,</hi> if your Friend hath a mind to trouble himself to that degree, he may <hi>present,</hi> as they would have him, those that are absent; but then let him take heed that he presents <hi>all that are absent every Sunday and Holiday:</hi> and begin first with the <hi>Parson</hi> if he doth not diligently read Service every <hi>Sunday</hi> and <hi>Holiday,</hi> then go on, and present every person for every day he is absent, or being there, spends his time irreverently, sleeping or prating. Let him not spare any one, <hi>Papist</hi> or <hi>Protestant, sick</hi> or <hi>well,</hi> at <hi>home</hi> or <hi>abroad,</hi> every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>that lieth in, every Nurse, every Servant,</hi> (provided they be above Sixteen years of age) and let him know, that if he be bound by his Oath to Present every one <hi>absent,</hi> he is as much bound to this as to any thing; for if the crime be <hi>meer absence,</hi> and he be bound to present all <hi>he knows are absent,</hi> his <hi>Oath</hi> tieth him to do this. Will they say, But you knew such and such were at <hi>London</hi> that day? Besides that none can know this; I would fain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand by what rule of Law an Officer may judge, that one who lives at <hi>Northampton</hi> hath a <hi>reasonable let or excuse,</hi> because it is said he is gone to <hi>London,</hi> more than if it be said he is gone to <hi>Abington:</hi> If absence from home, may by the Officer be judged a <hi>reasonable excuse,</hi> the greatness or smallness of the distance alters nothing the case. And let your Friend also Present offenders against all the Statutes, which are to be inquired of by such Justices; for he is by his Oath no more bound to Present offenders against one Statute than another. Advise him to present (whether it be in the <hi>Articles</hi> or no, they are not the <hi>Articles</hi> which are his Law) all those who he knows <hi>within Twenty days before have profanely sworn or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, who have been drunk, who have sate tipling in Alchouses above an hour, who have profaned the Sabbath, &amp;c.</hi> By this the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that love business, will find they have work enough to do.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96259:5"/>
            <p>This is, <hi>Sir,</hi> the best advice I can give you on the behalf of your Friend; you should do well to advise with greater Lawyers than my self: But yet I believe any of them will tell you I have <hi>spoken sense.</hi> There is nothing I so much abhor as <hi>arbitrary power;</hi> and I equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly detest one who hath the path of a Law cut out for him by a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and cannot keep to it; as him who hath been so long at a <hi>Tavern</hi> that he cannot keep his way in the Streets. The latter is drunk with <hi>Wine,</hi> the former with <hi>passion</hi> and <hi>folly:</hi> I say folly, for I never yet observed any Magistrate outrun the Law, but it threw up his heels as soon as a brisk <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> dared to pursue him and throw it at him. The Law is a steady thing, and keeps its vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour; mens passions are mutable and short-breath'd. The Law was made for a Rule of indiscriminitive justice, not to serve any mans turn to execute their silly passions; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever useth it to that purpose, will, first or last, find it an edged tool that will cut his Fingers that so abuseth it.</p>
            <p>If any man will be so hardy as to satisfie his private revenge, he will venture to break the Law (and let me tell you, the <hi>imprisonment of persons</hi> not <hi>warranted by Law,</hi> is one of the highest violations of it) in hope that if it comes to the worst, he shall get a <hi>Pardon</hi> or an <hi>Act of oblivion;</hi> he must remember, Neither of those will acquit him for any private wrong done to any; besides, they are very chargeable and incertain: And for any in those pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptions to break a <hi>Law,</hi> is but the same thing which <hi>Fuller</hi> saith, it is for a man to marry an old Widow, in hopes to bury her; <hi>viz. To hang himself, in hopes somebody may come and cut the halter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope, Sir, you will not make an ill use of any thing I have wrote to you; I do not mean, by <hi>communicating</hi> it to others; If I were with you, I would say the same thing that I say here, to those most concerned; but I mean in taking it, or any thing of it, to be a License to your Friend, or any else, not to go hear the <hi>Prayers of the Church.</hi> The Law is severe enough against them that do omit their duty in that point, though it directs a just method and order in which alone they may be punished, and will have none to be <hi>oppressed</hi> by any ones execution of his own <hi>will</hi> and <hi>passion,</hi> instead of what it directeth. What I have wrote is for the relief of your oppressed Friend, not for the incouragement of any transgressing Friend.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> I am
<signed>Your commandable Friend and Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>